New Haven Railroad Historical and Technical Association (NHRHTA) Map Collection
© 2006 University of Connecticut
New Haven Railroad Historical and Technical Association Map Collection.
undated, 1872-1930s.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
New Haven Railroad Historical and Technical Association.
2000 items.
Maps and track plans of property in Connecticut, Massachusetts, eastern New York, and Rhode Island belonging to the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad Company and its predecessors, including the Hartford & New Haven Railroad, the Housatonic Railroad, the Naugatuck Railroad, the New York & New England Railroad, and the New York & New Haven Railroad.
MSS19980377
History
The New Haven Railroad Historical and Technical Association is a railroad enthusiast organization founded in the late 1960s as the New Haven Railroad Technical Information Association. The group's purpose is to keep the history and spirit of the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad, better known as the New Haven Railroad, alive by accumulating and distributing historical, educational, and technical data specifically related to the railroad line and its predecessors.
The New Haven Railroad, formed in 1872 through the merger of the New York & New Haven Railroad and the Hartford & New Haven Railroad, achieved the region's early railroad developers long-desired wish for a link between Boston and New York City. Approximately one hundred small independent railroads were built in southern New England between 1826 and the 1880s and by 1904 the majority were absorbed, consolidated, or merged into the vast New Haven Railroad system. At its peak in 1929, the New Haven Railroad owned and operated 2,131 miles of track throughout eastern New York, Connecticut, Massachusetts, and Rhode Island. The railroad line, beset with financial difficulties after World War II, became defunct on January 1, 1969, when it was absorbed into the Penn Central Railroad.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of property and track plans of the railroads that became part of the New Haven Railroad system. The collection consists of two parts - maps identified by state and thereunder by town, and maps organized by the name of the predecessor line.
Arrangement
Series I: Town Maps ( undated, 1888-1929 ) includes property maps and track plans of railroad property belonging to the New Haven Railroad and its predecessors in selected towns in Connecticut, Massachusetts, eastern New York, and Rhode Island. The maps are organized alphabetically by state and thereunder by town.
Series II: Railroad Company (Land Title) Maps ( undated, 1872-1930s ) contains property maps for some of the railroad companies absorbed by the New Haven Railroad. The railroads include the following: Berkshire Railroad, Danbury and Norwalk Railroad, Harlem River and Port Chester Railroad, Hartford and Connecticut Western Railroad, Hartford and New Haven Railroad, Housatonic Railroad, Meriden and Waterbury Railroad, Naugatuck Railroad, New Haven and Derby Railroad, New Haven and Northampton Railroad, New York and New Haven Railroad, Poughkeepsie and Erie Railroad, Ridgefield Railroad, Shepaug Valley Railroad, Stamford and New Canaan Railroad, Stockbridge and Pittsfield Railroad, State Line Railroad, Turner's Falls Branch Railroad, Union Freight Railroad, and Watertown and Waterbury Railroad. The maps are organized alphabetically by railroad company and thereunder by the stretch between towns.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to New England railroads. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Organizations:
New Haven Railroad Historical and Technical Association.
Subjects:
Berkshire Railroad.; Danbury and Norwalk Railroad.; Harlem River and Port Chester Railroad.; Hartford and Connecticut Western Railroad.; Hartford and New Haven Railroad.; Housatonic Railroad.; Meriden and Waterbury Railroad.; Naugatuck Railroad.; New Haven and Derby Railroad.; New Haven and Northampton Railroad.; New York and New Haven Railroad.; New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad.; Poughkeepsie and Erie Railroad.; Ridgefield Railroad.; Shepaug Valley Railroad.; Stamford and New Canaan Railroad.; Stockbridge and Pittsfield Railroad.; State Line Railroad.; Turner’s Falls Branch Railroad.; Union Freight Railroad.; Watertown and Waterbury Railroad.
Document Types:
Maps.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
Detailed Description
- Series I: Town Maps, undated, 1888-1929
  - Connecticut
    - Andover, 1891 (Box 1:, Folder 1)
    - Bolton, 1891 (Box 1:, Folder 2)
    - Bristol, 1889 (Box 1:, Folder 3)
    - Brookfield, undated (Box 1:, Folder 4)
    - Chaplin, 1891 (Box 2:, Folder 5)
    - Columbia, 1891 (Box 2:, Folder 6)
    - Coventry, 1891 (Box 2:, Folder 7)
    - Danbury, 1890 (Box 2:, Folder 8)
    - East Hartford (2), 1888, 1891 (Box 2:, Folder 9)
    - East Windsor, 1888 (Box 3:, Folder 10)
    - Ellington, 1888 (Box 3:, Folder 11)
    - Enfield, 1888 (Box 3:, Folder 12)
    - Griswold, 1892 (Box 3:, Folder 13)
    - Hampton, 1890 (Box 3:, Folder 14)
    - Hartford, circa 1888 (Box 3:, Folder 15)
    - Manchester, 1891 (Box 4:, Folder 16)
    - Middlebury, undated (Box 4:, Folder 17)
    - New Britain, 1889 (Box 4:, Folder 18)
    - Newington, 1889 (Box 4:, Folder 19)
    - Newtown, undated (Box 4:, Folder 20)
    - Norwalk (Tax map), 1929 (Box 4:, Folder 21)
    - Oxford, 1889 (Box 5:, Folder 22)
    - Plainfield, 1892 (Box 5:, Folder 23)
    - Plainville, 1889 (Box 5:, Folder 24)
    - Pomfret, 1890 (Box 5:, Folder 25)
    - Portland, 1897-1898 (Box OS:, Folder 26)
    - Putnam, 1890 (Box 5:, Folder 27)
    - South Windsor, 1888 (Box 6:, Folder 28)
    - Southbury, 1890 (Box 6:, Folder 29)
    - Sterling, 1889 (Box 6:, Folder 31)
    - Thompson, 1890 (Box 6:, Folder 32)
    - Vernon (2), 1888, 1891 (Box 7:, Folder 33-34)
    - Hartford, 1889 (Box 7:, Folder 35)
    - Windham--Highland Division, 1891 (Box 7:, Folder 36)
    - Windham--Midland Division, 1891 (Box 7:, Folder 37)
  - Massachusetts
    - Longmeadow, 1888 (Box 8:, Folder 38)
    - Plymouth, 1889 (Box 8:, Folder 39)
    - Springfield, 1888 (Box 8:, Folder 40)
  - New York
    - Beekman, 1892 (Box 8:, Folder 41)
    - East Fishkill, 1892 (Box 9:, Folder 42)
    - Fishkill, undated (Box 9:, Folder 43)
    - Patterson, 1892 (Box 9:, Folder 44)
    - Pawling, 1892 (Box 9:, Folder 45)
    - Southeast, 1892 (Box 6:, Folder 30)
  - Rhode Island
    - Richmond, 1896 (Box 9:, Folder 46)
    - Warwick, undated (Box 9:, Folder 47)
- Series II: Railroad Company (Land Title) Maps, undated, 1872-1930s
  - Berkshire Railroad, Sheffield to Great Barrington, 1912 (Box 10:, Folder 48)
  - Danbury and Norwalk Railroad, Danbury to Redding, 1912 (Box 10:, Folder 49)
  - Danbury and Norwalk Railroad, Wilton to Norwalk, 1911 (Box 10:, Folder 50)
  - Harlem River and Port Chester Railroad, Harlem River to New Rochelle, 1912 (Box 10:, Folder 51)
  - Harlem River and Port Chester Railroad, New York City, 1908 (Box 10:, Folder 52)
  - Harlem River and Port Chester Railroad, New York City to New Rochelle, 1912 (Box 10:, Folder 53)
  - Hartford Flood Control, ca. 1930s (Box 11:, Folder 54)
  - Hartford and Connecticut Western Railroad, 1893 (Box 11:, Folder 55)
  - Hartford and New Haven Railroad, Berlin to Newington, 1910 (Box 11:, Folder 56)
  - Hartford and New Haven Railroad, Enfield to Springfield, 1910 (Box 11:, Folder 57)
  - Hartford and New Haven Railroad, West Hartford to Windsor, 1910 (Box 11:, Folder 58)
  - Hartford and New Haven Railroad, Windsor to Windsor Locks, 1910 (Box 11:, Folder 59)
  - Housatonic Railroad, Bridgeport to Monroe, 1911 (Box 12:, Folder 60)
  - Housatonic Railroad, Canaan to North Canaan, 1912 (Box 12:, Folder 61)
  - Housatonic Railroad, Cornwall, 1912 (Box 12:, Folder 62)
  - Housatonic Railroad, Kent, 1911 (Box 12:, Folder 63)
  - Housatonic Railroad, New Milford (2), 1912 (Box 12:, Folder 64)
  - Housatonic Railroad, Newtown to Brookfield, 1912 (Box 12:, Folder 65)
  - Meriden and Waterbury Railroad, Meriden to Waterbury, 1913 (Box 13:, Folder 66)
  - Naugatuck Railroad, Milford to Ansonia, 1911 (Box 13:, Folder 67)
  - Naugatuck Railroad, Torrington to Winchester, 1912 (Box 13:, Folder 68)
  - Naugatuck Railroad, Waterbury to Litchfield, 1912 (Box 13:, Folder 69)
  - New Haven and Derby Railroad, Derby to Ansonia, 1911 (Box 13:, Folder 70)
  - New Haven and Derby Railroad, New Haven to Orange, 1912 (Box 13:, Folder 71)
  - New Haven and Northampton Railroad, Hatfield to Conway, 1913 (Box 14:, Folder 72)
  - New Haven and Northampton Railroad, New Haven to Hamden, 1913 (Box 14:, Folder 73)
  - New Haven and Northampton Railroad, Northampton to Williamsburg, 1913 (Box 14:, Folder 74)
  - New Haven and Northampton Railroad, Plainville to Avon, 1913 (Box 14:, Folder 75)
  - New Haven and Northampton Railroad, Simsbury to Suffield, 1913 (Box 14:, Folder 76)
  - New Haven and Northampton Railroad, Southampton to Northampton, 1913 (Box 14:, Folder 77)
  - New Haven and Northampton Railroad, Southwick to Westfield, 1913 (Box 15:, Folder 78)
  - New York and New Haven Railroad, Bridgeport to Stratford, 1910 (Box 15:, Folder 79)
  - New York and New Haven Railroad, Greenwich, 190? (Box 15:, Folder 80)
  - New York and New Haven Railroad, Milford, 1910 (Box 15:, Folder 81)
  - New York and New Haven Railroad, New York City to Rye, undated (Box 15:, Folder 82)
  - New York and New Haven Railroad, New York City to Woodlawn, 1908 (Box 15:, Folder 83)
  - New York and New Haven Railroad, Orange to New Haven, 1910 (Box 16:, Folder 84)
  - New York and New Haven Railroad, Stamford to Norwalk, 1907 (Box 16:, Folder 85)
  - New York and New Haven Railroad, Westport to Fairfield, 1910 (Box 16:, Folder 86)
  - New York and New Haven Railroad, Woodlawn to Greenwich, 1919 (Box 16:, Folder 87)
  - New York, New Haven and Hartford Railroad, Miscellaneous Property, undated (Box 16:, Folder 88)
  - New York, Providence and Boston Railroad, Warwick, 1912 (Box 16:, Folder 89)
  - Poughkeepsie and Erie Railroad, undated (Box 17:, Folder 90)
  - Ridgefield Railroad, Ridgefield, 1912 (Box 17:, Folder 91)
  - Shepaug Valley Railroad, Litchfield to Washington, 1913 (Box 17:, Folder 92)
  - Shepaug Valley Railroad, Roxbury to Newtown, 1913 (Box 17:, Folder 93)
  - Stamford and New Canaan Railroad, Stamford to New Canaan, 190? (Box 17:, Folder 94)
  - Stockbridge and Pittsfield Railroad, Great Barrington to Lee, 1912 (Box 17:, Folder 95)
  - Stockbridge and Pittsfield Railroad, Lee to Pittsfield, undated (Box 17:, Folder 96)
  - State Line Railroad, Great Barrington to West Stockbridge, 1913 (Box 18:, Folder 97)
  - Turner's Falls Branch Railroad, Deerfield to Montague, 1913 (Box 18:, Folder 98)
  - Union Freight Railroad, Boston, 1872 (Box 18:, Folder 99)
  - Watertown and Waterbury Railroad, Waterbury to Watertown, 1912 (Box 18:, Folder 100)